是, 大臣  第2季第4集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译:Aries 校对&时间轴:tpring
缘竿而上
汉弗莱 你胡说什么?
Humphrey, what are you havering about?
没说什么 只说大臣不一定批准
I'm simply saying we can't take the Minister's approval for granted.
意大利政府出了份大合同
The Italian government have offered a massive contract
要我们在莫西塞德郡生产丙醇
to manufacture propanol at our Merseyside plant,
这份合同 让我们正要倒闭的工厂起死回生
which means saving a plant we were going to have to close,
免除失业 增加出口税
saving jobs, earning export royalties.
这还不明显?他非批不可      但如果大臣想...
He has to give us the go-ahead. But if the Minister thinks...
大臣哪会想事
Ministers don't think!
别跟我提大臣
Don't talk to me about Ministers.
我做了10年英国化工集团董事长
I've been chairman of British Chemical Corporation forten years,
一共跟19名大臣打过交道      天哪天哪
and in that time dealt with nineteen different Ministers.
他们总在瞎忙 没空见我
They've usually not had time to see me,
整天行贿工会领导人让他们别罢工
because they're too busy bribing Trade Union leaders not to strike.
得了 沃利 他们没行贿      真的吗?
They've never bribed anybody. Oh, no?
进公营机构吧 张三 当骑士吧 李四 领爵位吧 王五
"Have a quango, Tom; a knighthood, Dick; a peerage, Harry".
可大臣担心...      大臣他当然担心了
But the Minister's worried... Of course he's worried!
我要是不能让这些
If I'd neverdone anything to worry
胆小鬼 做秀家 拉票狂担心起来
those vote-grabbing baby-kissing jellies,
我们集团10年前就玩完了
we'd have gone down the tube ten years ago!
可你说丙醇含变性二恶英      那又如何?
But propanol contains metadioxin. So what?
二恶英在萨维索(意大利)泄漏过 会伤害胎儿
Dioxin was released at Seveso. It can damage the foetus.
二恶英归二恶英 变性二恶英是种非活性化合物
That's dioxin, for Christ's sake! Metadioxin is an inert compound.
华盛顿食品药物管理局都开出了安全证明
It's been given a clean bill of health by Washington.
你设立的亨德森委员会
The Henderson Committee, which you set up,
也会这么说的
will give it the OK, too.
我知道 沃利 但这名字可能有些政治敏感性
I know, Wally, but the name could be politically sensitive.
可我在提案里没提变性二恶英
But I've taken metadioxin out of the proposal.
单单是丙醇      你真英明
I call it propanol. Very wise of you.
你让我写的      那我真英明
You told me to. Very wise of me!
照我说 大臣不会反对的 只是手段问题
But the Ministermay raise no objections, it just needs tact.
好的 那就是没问题了
Fine. In that case, there's no problem.
我跟你去 使些手段
I'll have a tactful word with Hacker
亲自说服哈克那浆糊脑袋
and persuade the blancmange myself.
我觉得...不是我不信你 沃利
Don't take this amiss, Wally,
幸运的话 凭我就能说服他
but I might just be able to manage
不用你那种...自成一家的...手段
without your unique... brand of tact.
多好的消息啊 汉弗莱      是 大臣
This is wonderful news, Humphrey. Yes, Minister.
濒临倒闭的工厂 一夜间成了化工集团的摇钱树
We turn a run-down plant from loss-maker into a profitable unit,
他们成了欧洲最大的丙醇工厂
the largest manufacturer of propanol in Europe.
是 大臣      英国制造的领先设备
Yes, Minister. Equipment made in UK factories.
地方政府得益 出口贸易交流
Income for the local authorities, foreign exchange from exports.
好得不像真的      确实是真的 大臣
Too good to be true! It is true.
丙醇真好...到底什么是丙醇?
Good old propanol... What is propanol, actually?
很有意思 丙醇从前用二恶英制造
It used to be made with dioxin
自从意大利萨维索泄漏事故
until the Seveso explosion
之后就重新开发了安全化合物 名为变性二恶英
then they developed a safe compound, metadioxin.
意大利的工厂被封闭 得请英国化工集团来制造
Italian factory is sealed off so they've asked the BCC to make it.
算他们倒霉      确实有点
An ill wind. Quite so.
这东西真的安全吧?     绝对安全     那就好
But this stuff is perfectly safe? Perfectly.
软弱的大臣或许会对相似名字抱以怀疑
Weak Ministers might have doubts over the similarity of the names,
但有骨气的大臣不会
but no one with any backbone would be deflected
拒绝如此有利的项目
from such a beneficial project
就为这点细枝末节
on such a useless pretext.
可不是 我知道那种大臣 政治软脚虾
I know just the sort of Minister you mean. Political jellyfish.
不敢做决策 生怕招惹谁
Terrified of taking any decision.
反正 决策总会得罪人的
Afterall, every decision upsets someone, doesn't it?
尽责的政府做出正确决策
Good government is doing what's right
而不是受欢迎的 是吧汉弗莱?
not just what's popular.
所言极是 大臣      不过这会受欢迎吧?
Absolutely, Minister. But this will be popular?
肯定大受欢迎      汉弗莱 确认一下
Very popular. Humphrey, I want to be sure.
你不是要我展现魄力吧?
You're not asking me to make a courageous decision, are you?
绝对没有 大臣 这说哪里话
Of course not, Minister.
那就好 要提上内阁吗?
Good, good. Should I take it to Cabinet?
我觉得越低调越好      为什么?
I think the less said, the better. Why?
尽管变性二恶英完全无害
Although metadioxin is totally harmless,
这名称可能会让无知的人紧张
the name may cause anxiety in ignorant minds.
汉弗莱 你是说我的内阁同僚?
Humphrey, you're talking about my Cabinet colleagues.
我说的是"地球之友"组织      这倒是
I was referring to the Friends of the Earth.
喂? 琼·利特勒来了 大臣 她是西南利物浦的议员
Yes? Joan Littlerhas arrived, MP for Liverpool South West.
好的 她来有何打算?
Know what she wants?
当然 她是首相的政务次官
She's the Prime Minister's PPS,
新工厂坐落于她的选区
and the new plant is in her constituency.
好 让她进来 汉弗莱你先出去好吗?
Showher in. If you'll excuse us?
首相政务次官? 我还是留下吧
The PM's PPS? I think I'll stay.
琼·利特勒 大臣 西南利物浦的议员
Joan Littler, memberfor Liverpool South West.
琼 你认识汉弗莱·阿普比吗?     很高兴见到您
Do you know Humphrey Appleby? Delighted to meet you.
快坐下
Do take a seat.
谢谢 伯纳      伯纳
Thank you, Bernard. Bernard...
好吧 有什么我能效劳的?
Now, what can I do foryou?
吉姆 化工集团要把我的选区怎样?
Jim, what's the BCC up to in my constituency?
即将启动一项振奋人心的新项目 促进就业和投资
They'll be announcing a very exciting project, with new jobs.
对 但有些很可怕的传闻
Yes... but there's some very worrying rumours.
比如?      有关有害化学品
Such as? Rumours of dangerous chemicals.
化学品都有害
All chemicals are dangerous...
大臣说那是空穴来风 不必担心
The Ministermeans the rumours are unfounded, no cause for alarm.
我不管 你能保证先做公开调查吗?
Can I have your assurance there'll be a full public enquiry?
调查一下也不错
Not a bad idea...
大臣是说完全不必公开调查
The Ministerwas about to say there's no need foran enquiry.
已经在研究了 近期会公布报告
A report will be issued shortly.
听好 我是来问吉姆的
I came here to talk to Jim.
你是在问他啊      可都是你替他答的
You are talking to him. But he's not answering, you are!
大臣与我想法一致      谁的想法 你的?
The Ministerand I are of one mind. Whose? Yours?
我听说就是这种产品污染了意大利萨维索
I've heard this factory made the chemical that poisoned Seveso!
没那事      是吗?
That's not true. Isn't it?
萨维索那是二恶英 这是变性二恶英
The chemical in Seveso was dioxin. This is metadioxin.
还不是一样      名字相似而已
That's virtually the same thing. Just a similar name.
只不过前面加了变性两字
It's the same name with "meta" stuck on the front.
这就大不相同了      为什么 变性是什么意思?
That makes all the difference. Why? What does "meta" mean?
变性什么意思 汉弗莱?
What does "meta" mean, Humphrey?
简单 意思是"副" "后"或"超"
"With", "after" or "beyond".
词源来自希腊 就是"后二恶英"或"超二恶英"
From the Greek, of course. "After" dioxin or "beyond" dioxin.
如果用宾格 就是"超"或"后"
If it's in the accusative, it's "beyond orafter",
用所有格就是"副" 拉丁语也是 您当然记得
with the genitive it's "with", as in Latin, as you no doubt recall.
"副"作前缀就得用离格
The ablative is used forwords needing "with" to precede them.
不过当然 希腊语没有离格
But of course, there isn't an ablative in Greek.
说得好 伯纳      谢谢
Well done, Bernard. Thank you.
明白了吧?      不 不明白
You see? Not exactly, no.
我觉得挺清楚的      我想知道的是
I thought thatwas perfectly plain. What I insist on knowing
这两种药品的本质区别何在
is what is the actual difference between dioxin and metadioxin.
好说 变性二恶英是二恶英的一种非活性化合物
Metadioxin is an inert compound of dioxin.
我好像明白了 汉弗莱
I think I follow that, Humphrey,
不过你能不能再解释清楚一点?
but could you explain it a little more clearly?
哪一方面 大臣?      非活性是什么意思?
In what sense, Minister? What does "inert" mean?
就是它没...
It means it's not...
活性
... ert.
连只苍蝇都"活"不了
Wouldn't "ert" a fly.
你说什么 伯纳?      没什么 大臣
What did you say, Bernard? Nothing, Minister.
实际应用中什么意思?
What does that mean in practical terms?
你是说化学上?
You mean chemically?
对 化学上     化学上怎么说?
Yes, chemically. What does it mean chemically?
我不知道怎么用通俗语言解释
I can't explain it in layman's language...
你懂化学吗?      当然不懂 大臣
Do you know any chemistry? Of course not, Minister.
我是拿奖学金项目的
I was in the scholarship form.
古典文学系
Classics.
化合物又是什么?     你也不懂化学?
And what's a compound? Don't you know any chemistry?
不懂 你呢?
No. Do you?
我们应该懂点 对吧?      化合物就是...
We ought to, oughtn't we? A compound is a...
你们都知道复合利息吧?
You know what compound interest is?
对对 让人高兴的东西
Yes, well, a jolly good thing.
化合物大概就这意思
That's the sort of thing a compound is.
就是这样
That's it, then.
总而言之 我们已经达成共识
To sum up, I think we're all of the same mind, broadly speaking.
可以批准了
We're ready to go ahead.
我可没这么说过
I've said no such thing!
我们都同意 只是名称问题
The only difference is in the name,
二恶英和变性二恶英 就像利特勒和希特勒
dioxin and metadioxin, like... Littlerand Hitler.
总不会因为名字像 你为人也像他吧
Not that you're like Hitler because yourname's similar!
重点不在这里      那在哪里?
That's not the point. What is the point?
重点是 这工厂在我选区里
The point is this factory is in my constituency!
这会给选区带来更多资金和就业
It'll be good forthe constituency, more jobs, more money.
我们最多得罪几个杞人忧天的环保主义者
The only people we'll offend are a few environmentalists.
顶多...百来张票
At most, it won't cost us more than 100 votes.
我的多数票只有91票
My majority is 91.
还不提旁边3个边缘选区票更少
Not to mention the three marginal constituencies bordering mine!
说到这个 我能不能再插一句?
Could I intervene just once more?
化工集团这个丙醇项目可是倍受期待
The case forthe BCC manufacturing propanol is overwhelming.
倍受期待
Overwhelming.
好工作 高收入 出口订单也跑不了
Great jobs, increased income and secure, profitable export orders.
出口订单      另外
Export orders. Furthermore...
华盛顿食品药品局宣布该产品安全
The drug has been declared safe by Washington,
华盛顿      我们也在准备相关报告
Washington. We're preparing a report, too.
大臣坚信
The Minister is confident
这个项目能使你的选区乃至全国受益
this scheme is to the advantage of constituency and country.
如果证实了不安全 我也不会批
If it proves not to be safe, I won't allow its manufacture here.
可如果报告说它安全 不批就亏了 是吧?
But if the report says it is safe, that'd be absurd, wouldn't it?
我可不服气 吉姆
I'm not satisfied with that, Jim.
记住 是政党让你作议员
Rememberthat the party made you an MP,
如果下次政党落选 你也别当大臣了
and you can't be a Minister if your party loses the next election.
您还是不放心 大臣
You still don't look happy, Minister.
看起来行 可如果报告没你说的那么准
Suppose the report isn't as conclusive as you say.
谁是亨德森 我要不要去见见他?      没必要
Oughtn't I to meet this Henderson? No need.
亨德森教授是剑桥优秀生化专家 我们精心挑选的
He's a brilliant Cambridge biochemist, chosen with some care.
如果他的报告说"有待观望"呢?
Suppose he produces a cautious, wait-and-see report?
那我们不公布 改用美国报告
We don't publish it. We use the American report instead.
很好很好
Fine!
你是说禁掉它?      当然不是 只是不公布而已
You mean we suppress it? No, we just don't publish it.
有什么区别?      区别可大了
What's the difference? All the difference in the world!
查禁是独裁专政的手段
Suppression is the instrument of dictatorships.
我们自由国家不讲这些
We don't talk of that sort of thing in a free country.
我们经民主程序决议不公布
We take a democratic decision not to publish.
好 那我对媒体和议会怎么说?
Fine. What am I to say to the press and parliament?
"我们期待报告说这个决策很英明"
"We hoped the report would say it was a wise decision.
"但它说不行 所以我们当它不存在"
But we've cocked it up so we'll pretend the report doesn't exist".
很好笑 大臣      那该怎么说?
Very droll. What would I say?
有一套官方程序用来查禁...
There's a Government procedure for suppress...
决议不公布报告      真的?
...deciding not to publish reports. Really?
当然 只要降低它的可信性
You simply discredit them.
老天啊
Good heavens!
怎么做?
How?
第一步 从公众利益角度出发
Stage One, give your reasons in terms of the public interest.
暗示存在泄密隐患      我记个笔记行吗?
Hint at security considerations... Mind if I make a note?
好像很有用 可以拿来
This could be useful for discrediting
打发党内某些笨蛋的研究文件
some of the party's idiotic research documents.
指出该报告将给政府施加压力 引起误解
The report could put pressure on Government and be misinterpreted.
什么都可能被误解 耶酥的山上宝训也逃不过
Anything could be misinterpreted. The Sermon on the Mount could be!
确实 如果山上宝训是政府文件 绝对不宜发表
Indeed the Sermon should not have been published.
该文件非常不负责任
A most irresponsible document.
那套善有善报的说法
All that stuff about the meek inheriting the earth
有可能严重降低国防预算
could do irreparable damage to the defence budget.
我看也是 还有吗?
I suppose you're right. What else?
然后说 最好等待长期具体报告
Say it's better to wait for a more detailed study over longertime.
如果没有呢?      那更好 自己派人写
Suppose there isn't one? Commission one.
更加游刃有余
Gives you even more time to play with.
这些都是第一步?      对 在第二阶段
All this is Stage One? Yes. In Stage Two...
推翻那些你未公开的证据
discredit the evidence you're not publishing.
没公开怎么推翻?      大臣 没公开更好推翻
How, if you're not publishing it? It's easier if it's not published.
给媒体透个风 当然是小道消息
Do it by press leaks, of course, not directly.
说有些重要问题尚待解决
Say it leaves important questions unanswered,
证据说服力不强
the evidence is inconclusive,
数据可以有别的阐释
the figures are open to other interpretations,
某些研究结果自相矛盾
that certain findings are contradictory,
某些重点结论被人质疑
and that some of the main conclusions have been questioned.
要是没人质疑呢?      自己质疑啊
Suppose they haven't? Then question them!
这不就有了
Then they have!
要提出质疑 得仔细读懂它吧
But you'd have to go through it with a fine-toothed comb.
不用不用 没读过也能提
No, no, no. You'd say all these things without reading it.
凡是报告 都有没解决的问题
There's always some questions unanswered.
比如说?      那些还没提出来的问题啊
Such as? The ones that weren't asked.
第二步结束?      对 第三步
That's Stage Two? Yes. In Stage Three...
贬低报告中的建议
you undermine recommendations.
说它不足以作为长期计划的基础
"Not a basis for long-term decisions.
没有足够信息
Not sufficient information
进行有效评估
on which to base a valid assessment".
当前政策并不需要推翻重来
"Not really any need for a fundamental rethink of policies".
总的来说 与现有做法区别不大 就这么简单
"Broadly speaking, endorses current practice". It's easy.
有用吗?      几乎次次成功
That works? Nearly always.
没成功怎么办?      那就进入第四步
Suppose it doesn't? Move on to Stage Four.
还有四?
Stage Four?
第四步 质疑报告撰写者
Discredit the man who produced the report.
当然不能明说
Off the record.
暗示他对政府早已不满 或者想出风头
Say that he's harbouring a grudge against the Government
更有甚者 说他为跨国公司
or, betterstill, that he used to be a consultant
做过顾问
to a multi-national company.
他没做过呢?      那就是想做
Supposing he wasn't? Then he's hoping to be.
人人都想做跨国公司顾问
Everybody's hoping to be a consultant to a multi-national.
要么他觊觎爵位 或学院院长职位
Orhe's trying for a knighthood orvice-chancellorship.
大臣您看 可能性多了去了
There are endless possibilities.
打扰一下 大臣
Excuse me.
宣传办来电话 说丙醇工厂上了新闻
The press officerrang to say there's an item on the news.
好好 快开电视 我怎么不知道有
Yes, yes. Why wasn't I told?
化工集团没有义务向我们报告
The BCC aren't obliged to clear itwith us.
默西赛德地区爆发了骚乱
A rowhas blown up on Merseyside
抗议特批意大利政府委托化工集团
about a plan for the BCC to manufacture propanol
在该地区生产丙酮
under licence forthe Italian government.
很明显 丙醇内含变性二恶英
Apparently, propanol contains metadioxin,
化工集团宣称其无毒无害
which the BCC claims to be completely harmless.
然而 这是二恶英的化合物
It is a compound of dioxin,
二恶英曾在意大利萨维索泄漏
the chemical released after an explosion at Seveso
于1976年7月
in July 1976,
毒雾扩散到方圆4英里内
spreading poisonous dust over a 4-mile radius.
今天 默西赛德抗议者们在工厂门外疾呼
On Merseyside, protesters voiced their opposition to the BCC scheme
抗议化工集团的计划
outside the factory gates.
我跟你说 我们要怎样
I'll tell you what we'll do.
叫沃利爵士带上他的毒药赶紧滚蛋
Sir Wally can take his poison chemicals somewhere else!
我闺女还有3个月就生娃了
I've a daughter expecting a baby,
我可不想要个怪胎孙子
and my grandchild's not gonna be deformed
便宜那些意大利佬
for them bloody Eyeties'sake!
政府若把我们小民放在眼里 他们绝不会批准
If the Government cared about people, they'd never allow it!
化工集团称 丙醇的安全性报告
The BCC said a report on the safety of propanol
近期将由行政事务部发布
was due to be published shortly by Administrative Affairs.
下面是国际新闻 今天...
And now abroad again...
这变性二恶英简直是炸药
This metadioxin is dynamite.
大臣 我保证它完全无害
It's totally harmless.
化学上无害 政治上有害
Only chemically, not politically.
它伤不了人      它能把我报销掉
It can't hurt anyone. It could finish me off!
喂? 大臣 10号找您
Yes? Minister, Number 10 on the phone.
是政治部 首相刚刚看了新闻
The political office, the PM's just seen the news.
你好 我是吉姆
Hello, Jim here!
对 我刚才也看了
Yes, I just saw that, too.
地方上有点困难 别太担心
We don't need to be too worried about a little local difficulty.
想想就业机会和出口利益
Not in view of the jobs and exports...
不 没那么多岗位
No, not many jobs.
90来个吧 我觉得
Ninety, I think.
对 可是...
Yes, but...
你当然了
You do, do you?
对 好吧
Yes, well...
我也刚想这么说呢 对对
I was coming round to that viewpoint myself.
汉弗莱
Humphrey...
我突然想到一件事情      我看出来了
Something just struck me. I noticed.
你看 这项计划的争议很大
There are arguments against this scheme.
大臣 您已经同意...      对 但它可能损害
Minister, you've already agreed... It could lead to a loss of...
公信力      您说选票?
...public confidence. You mean votes?
选票? 不不 和选票无关 不用考虑它
Votes? No, no. It's not the votes that are a consideration at all.
但是你看 这是公众的意愿
But you see, it's the public will.
我们提倡民主
This is a democracy...
人民并不同意      人民既愚昧又盲目
and the people don't like it. They are ignorant and misguided.
汉弗莱 就是人民选出我的
It was the people who elected me!
大臣 事情在一周之后就能平息
In a week, the whole thing will have blown over,
一年之后 莫西塞德工厂将安全成功地运营着
and in a year's time, we'll have a safe and successful factory.
一周对政治算长的 汉弗莱
Aweek's a long time in politics.
一年对政府算短的
A year's a short time in Government.
你属于政府 我属于政治 现在首相很生气
You're in Government, I'm in politics and the PM is not pleased.
大臣 尽管我极其尊敬...      又想讽刺我了?
With the greatest respect... Going to insult me again?
可以说您把政党置于国家之上
You're putting party before country.
又是这陈词滥调?没点新鲜的吗?
Can't you think of a new clich?
大臣 "新鲜的陈词滥调"恐怕自相矛盾
Minister, a new clich?could be said to be a contradiction in terms.
汉弗莱 你不懂 你的生活安稳有保障
Humphrey, you lead a sheltered life.
而我必须在政坛存活 我才不得罪首相
I intend to survive and I'm not crossing the PM.
大臣 您为什么一定要顺竿爬?
Why must you be so concerned with climbing the greasy pole?
这很重要 我必须爬
The greasy pole is important. I have to climb it.
为什么?
Why?
因为有竿在那里
'Cause it's there!
请接泰晤士报的编辑 谢谢你 伯纳
The editor of the Times, please. Thank you, Bernard.
怎么泰晤士报比我还先看到报告?
How come the Times knows about the report before I do?
有人泄漏出去 大臣      我也知道
There's been a leak. I know that!
这是机密 我昨晚才拿到草案
Itwas "Confidential". I only got a draft last night.
幸好不是"内参"      为什么?
At least itwasn't "Restricted". Why?
"内参"的话昨天就见报了
"Restricted" means itwas in the papers yesterday.
"机密"才拖到今天
"Confidential" means it won't be in the papers till today.
谁泄漏的?汉弗莱?
Who leaked this? Humphrey?
我确定不是他 大臣      真的?
I'm sure he didn't, Minister. Are you?
大概不是他      是吗?
He probably didn't. No?
可能是其他人      这些泄漏真是耻辱
It might have been someone else. These leaks are a disgrace!
人民会以为是政客干的      本来也是这样
People think it's the politicians. It has been known.
依我看 我们漏的远没有被漏的多
In my opinion, we're farmore leaked against than leaking.
"政治懦夫否决化工集团提案 明哲保身"
"Political cowardice to reject the BCC proposal".
"哈克别无选择"
"Hackerhas no choice".
汉弗莱以为能让我负责 是吗?
Humphrey thinks he's got me committed!
这是非官方消息 漏的是草案
It's an unofficial leak of a draft report.
您无需负责
You're committed to nothing.
研究报告向着您吗?
Does the report give you a way out?
顺便 大臣 沃利·麦克弗兰爵士要见您
SirWally McFarlane is waiting to see you.
好吧 不过他来也白来
All right. But he's wasting his time.
沃利爵士 请进      谢谢您 早安
Come in, please, Sir Wally. Thank you. Morning.
早安      我能参加吗 大臣?
Morning. May I join you, Minister?
想来就来吧 请坐      谢谢 吉姆
Lf you like. Do sit down. Thank you, Jim.
那么      谢谢 伯纳
Now... Thank you, Bernard.
对不起
Sorry about that.
我看报了 亨德森报告明确支持我们
I see from the press the Henderson Report comes clearly on ourside.
我也看见了      那研究组漏得像筛子
I've seen that, too. That committee leaks like a sieve.
好了大臣 那新工厂就没阻力了
So there's no real case for refusing permission for the new plant.
我不太确定      听好 吉姆
I'm not sure yet. Now look, Jim...
这合同花费我们两年心血 至关重要
We've been working on this for two years, it's very important.
我是董事长兼化学家 我告诉你 变性二恶英无毒
I'm the chairman, and I tell you as a chemist, metadioxin is safe.
怎么你们专家总以为自己没错?
You experts always think you're right.
难不成门外汉了解得更清楚?
The more inexpert you are, the more likely you are to be right?
大臣们不是专家
Ministers are not experts.
选他们就是因为他们无知
They're chosen because they know nothing.
你承认啦?
You admit that?
对技术细节一无所知
Nothing about technical details.
大臣必须为国家大局着想 所以我还不确定
Ministers must take a broaderview, that's why I cannot commit yet.
听着 哈克
Look, Hacker!
你在犯错误 你心里清楚
This is the wrong decision and you know it.
懦弱 没骨气
It's cowardly and craven!
我不是懦夫      给我坐下
I am not cowardly... Sit down!
不就是为了那几个选区的几张选票吗?
You'll lose a few votes from a few people in those constituencies?
这是可悲      这是政治
It's pathetic! It's politics!
没错
Exactly!
我要上报工业部长
I'll be writing to the Secretary of State for Industry.
你不批项目我就辞职
I am prepared to resign if you block this one!
这下您意下如何 大臣?
How do you feel that went, Minister?
再选一个董事长不就完了      再选一个?
We'll have to get another chairman. Get another?
没人想接手这份工作
Nobody would accept a job like that!
没人想管国营企业 这是自取灭亡
Nobody wants to be chairman of nationalised industry: Instant ruin
最好上任当天就拿遣散费走人 早晚一样
They may as well accept the golden handshake the day they start.
总能找到一个      找个研究老年病的美国废物
We'll find someone. Some useless American geriatric.
不见得
Not necessarily.
正经人谁敢接手工业部门
How do you expect to find a decent replacement,
如果他的前任为正确决策而被迫辞职
when we forced his predecessor to resign fortaking a sound decision,
而且还是政治原因?
which we blocked for political reasons?
又是这套 我别无选择啊      大臣可以随心所欲
I have no choice. A Minister can do what he likes.
民主至上
It's the people's will.
我是他们的领头人 应该跟他们走
I am their leader. I must follow them.
我良心清白 两手干净
My hands are clean.
我觉得一个人见竿就爬
I thought itwas rather difficult to keep one's hands clean
想两手干净也难
while climbing the greasy pole.
伯纳 得阻止沃利闹事
We must stop Wally making a fuss.
他会在记者招待会上骂我目光短浅
Press conferences accusing me of lack of faith.
还有全景周刊采访(左翼刊物)     我该怎么办?
Interviews on Panorama. What am I to do?
如果我不批 泰晤士报和每日邮报会骂我政治懦夫
If I stop it, the Times will accuse me of political cowardice.
如果我批了 镜报和太阳报又会说我扼杀胎儿
If I let it, the Mirror will say I'm murdering unborn babies.
要是报告说变性二恶英不安全就好了
If only the report had any doubt about the safety of metadioxin.
它肯定不会说吗 大臣?      目前是没有
Are you sure it doesn't, Minister? Not as it stands.
伯纳 亨德森是剑桥的学者?      是
Henderson's a Cambridge man? Yes.
哪所学院?      国王学院 怎么?
Which college? King's. Why?
没事 就想看看是不是我的校友
Nothing. Just wondered if it was my old college.
您不是伦敦政治经济学院毕业的吗?
Weren't you at the LSE?
对对 没错
Yes, so I was.
你有他的档案吗 伯纳?      有 报告里附了
Have you got his file? It's with the report.
给我接剑桥大学       大臣 您应该知道
Got a Cambridge telephone...? You do realise,
当然您不是蓄意的
not that you have any such intention,
但您不应该干涉
but it would be most improper to influence
这种独立报告吧?
an independent report of this nature?
太不应该了 绝对的
Most improper! Out of the question.
我只想去国王学院 会会老朋友
Just it might be nice to pop down to have tea with my old friend,
RA克利顿 国王学院院长 接他的电话
R.A. Crichton, Provost of King's. Get him on the phone.
是 大臣 请接剑桥大学
Yes, Minister. Get me King's College, Cambridge.
谁知道 没准亨德森教授也会去喝茶
Who knows? Professor Henderson might drop in for tea.
无巧不成书嘛 是吧?
That'd be a happy coincidence, wouldn't it?
太正常了 学院同事嘛      这就没什么不妥了吧?
Perfectly natural. Nothing improper about that.
巧遇有什么不妥的?      我也这么觉得
How can a coincidence be improper? Myfeeling entirely.
喂
Yes?
请找克利顿院长
Lord Crichton, please.
从下院升到上院感觉如何?
How's the move from the Commons to the Lords?
像从动物界进了植物界
Like moving from animals to vegetables.
亨德森教授来了      谢谢 见到你太高兴了
Professor Henderson's here. Good to see you.
来见见我的老朋友 吉姆·哈克
Come and meet an old friend, Jim Hacker.
吉姆 这位是亨德森教授      亨德森教授
Jim, this is Professor Henderson. Professor Henderson!
真没想到 大臣也在这里
I didn't expect to see the Minister.
瞧这巧劲      是啊 真巧啊
What a coincidence! Yes, what a coincidence!
你们认识?      第一次见面
You know each other? We haven't met.
我在为他们部写报告      那真巧呢
I'm writing a report forhim. Well, what a coincidence.
是啊 真巧      巧得不能再巧了
Yes, what a coincidence! Extraordinary coincidence.
您对我的报告还满意吧?      当然 非常满意
You're happy with my report? Absolutely. Delighted.
你一定下了不少功夫
You must've worked very hard.
大部分都归功于华盛顿食品药物管理局
Most of it was done by Washington.
失陪 我去给我老婆倒杯茶
Excuse me, I'll go and help with the tea.
说说看 你原来写过政府报告吗?
Tell me, have you everwritten a Government report before?
没有      你的名字会载入史册
No. Yourname will be on it forever.
"亨德森报告"
"Henderson Report".
有点不朽的意味      这我倒没想过
It's a kind of immortality. I hadn't thought of it like that.
但报告万一出了差错      差错?
But if it were to go wrong... Go wrong?
如果变性二恶英没你说的那么安全
If this metadioxin isn't as safe as you say...
你的前途...
your career...
非常勇气可嘉
Very courageous!
各标准化测试都显示不存在致畸形毒素
None of the standard tests show evidence of teratogenic toxicity.
标准化测试?原来如此      您想说什么?
Standard tests? Quite. What do you mean?
你看 来时我在火车上记了些问题
Well, I was making a few notes on the train coming down.
尽管我不是生化学家 但似乎
I'm not a biochemist, but it would appear
美国报告中有些重要问题没解决
that the US report leaves some important questions unanswered.
有些证据说服力不强 有些结论被人质疑
Some evidence is inconclusive, some findings have been questioned,
数据可以作别的阐释      所有数据都...
the figures are open to interpretation,
长期深入研究或许会有不同发现
and different results might come from a more detailed study.
当然...      对对 可一旦报告有误
Obviously, but... But if anything did go wrong,
就算十年后出了事 媒体头一个就找你的报告
a delayed effect, the press would go straight to your report.
如果被查出你曾经...比如
And if it turned out that you'd everdone...
为跨国药品公司做过研究
laboratory trials fora multi-national drug company...
那都过去15年了      14年
Thatwas 15 years ago. 14.
你也知道媒体的可怕
You know what the press is like.
空穴来风 那麻烦可不小
No smoke without a fire. It could be a millstone!
一旦出差错 通俗杂志可要大放厥词
The popular press would be merciless, if anything went wrong:
"亨德森报告的牺牲品们辗转求死"
"Death Agony of Henderson Report Victims".
是
Yes...
是啊
Yes...!
我能怎么办呢?
I don't know what to do!
我不能篡改证据 它确实无毒 报告得承认
I can't alterthe evidence, the report says it's a safe drug.
确实 你没办法了      打扰二位一下
Quite. I see you have no choice. Stop talking shop.
经济学教授急着想与您交谈      是吗
Our Professor of Economics is dying to talk to you.
在为报告的事烦心?我原来写过不少
You're not worried about this report? I've done lots of these
改结论就行 媒体只看那个
It's the phrasing of the conclusion, that's all the press everread.
结尾怎么写的?
Now... how does it end?
我说 据已有证据 委员会没有理由拒绝该项目
"On existing evidence, there is no reason not to proceed".
好吧 这个结论只需要稍加润色
Well, it's just a question of a tidy bit of re-drafting.
"尽管就现有证据 委员会"
"While the committee feel there's no reason
"认为该项目可行"
not to proceed on existing evidence,
"仍需强调 变种二恶英问世未久"
it must be emphasised that metadioxin is a recent compound,
"不可贸然否认 若经长期研究"
and itwould be irresponsible to deny, after further research,
"也许会发现该产品危害人体健康"
its manufacture might be proved to be associated with health risks".
是 这结论能讲通
Yes, that seems perfectly fair.
你能不能再说一遍?
Could you just say that again?
与其那样 不如我给你写下来吧
Better than that... I'll jot it down for you.
行政事务部大臣 詹姆斯·哈克
The Minister for Administrative Affairs, James Hacker,
对外宣布他不会支持
has announced he'll not give approval
英国化工集团制造丙醇
for the BCC to make propanol.
亨德森报告虽认为该药物大体安全
The Henderson Committee, while generally approving the drug,
却承认经长远研究 也许会发现其有害
said it could not deny that future research might disclose risks.
哈克先生今天访问该工厂时发表了这一讲话
Mr Hackermade his announcement today while visiting BCC's factory,
受到群众热烈欢迎
where he was greeted by an enthusiastic crowd.
体育方面 继昨日大胜...
And now sport. Following last night's defeat...
怎样 大臣
Well, Minister?
怎样 汉弗莱
Well, Humphrey?
您觉得您像个英雄?      是啊
Do you feel like a hero? Indeed I do.
首相一定很满意      我见过的最糟的政府决策
And Number 10 will be delighted. One of the worst decisions ever!
这是我做过的最好的政治决策
And one of the best political decisions I've made.
你觉得呢 伯纳
What do you think, Bernard?
这个...
Well...
综观多方因素 全面考虑
bearing everything in mind and after due consideration...
总而言之 统而言之
considering all the implications and points of view...
总统而言之 一言以蔽之
well, in otherwords, in fact, I am bound to say...
您非常上镜 大臣
you look awfully good on television, Minister.
汉弗莱 能不能给亨德森颁个巴思勋章?
Humphrey, can we manage a CBE for Henderson?
没门 他这人缺乏判断力 完全靠不住
Certainly not! He's unreliable and lacking in judgement.
我不明白他怎么就在
I can't think why he cast doubt
报告末尾突然转向
on his whole report in that final paragraph.
我觉得他判断准确 高大伟岸 极富人格魅力
He has excellent judgement, enormous stature and great charm.
我记得您说您没见过他
I thought you said you'd nevermet him.
是说他境界伟岸 汉弗莱
I meant intellectual stature, Humphrey.
人格魅力呢?
And charm?
笔下魅力
He writes with charm.
是不是 伯纳?
Doesn't he, Bernard?
噢 是 大臣
Oh, yes, Minister.